Guide to the Joseph L. Miller Photographs Collection 1909-1995
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Joseph L. Miller photographs collection
1909-1995
1971-1995
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Org. Lot 1021
Miller, Joseph L., 1910-
0.84 cubic feet 502 photographs, 33 slides, 67 film negatives, 2 postcards, and other printed material in 1 document box and 3 oversize folders
Photographs document Joseph L. Miller's crusade to protect the Bull Run Reserve and watershed from logging and recreation damage and to expand public awareness of the threat to its famed pristine water, which is the main source of water for Portland, Or., and other smaller communities in the area. The bulk of the photographs show the impact of logging on the watershed.
Biographical Note
Joseph L. Miller (1910- ), a native of Chicago, trained as a medical doctor. He moved to Oregon in 1940 with his wife, Amy, and he opened a medical practice in Portland, Or. In 1948, the family bought 94 acres near the Bull Run Reserve, in the vicinity of Marmot, Clackamas County, Oregon. There they built a small cabin, mostly for summer camping, and in 1975 established a permanent home on three acres. They donated the remaining 91 acres to the Portland Audubon Society in 1977.
In 1971, Miller discovered that the United States Forest Service (USFS) had, since 1958, allowed commercial logging in the watershed in spite of a 1904 Trespass Act and planned to open a 30,000-acre area for recreational purposes. Such strong opposition was expressed at a public meeting, which Miller attended, that the USFS and the Portland Water Bureau withdrew the plan. Miller then began a systematic effort to collect and disseminate information on the Bull Run Reserve to focus public attention on the need for watershed protection. In 1974, he organized the Bull Run Citizens' Advisory Committee, which evolved into the Bull Run Interest Group (BRIG) by 1975. BRIG was active at varying levels until about 1993. Miller was most concerned about the secrecy and lack of public information and input that he believed characterized the activities of the USFS and Portland Water Bureau, which managed the Bull Run Watershed.
In 1975, Miller and two co-plaintiffs initiated a class-action lawsuit against the USFS for allowing public access and logging in violation of the Trespass Act and won their case. However, in 1977 Congress nullified the act, and new legislation, introduced by Rep. Robert Duncan and Sen. Mark Hatfield of Oregon, specified that the Bull Run Reserve could be managed by the Forest Service according to prevailing multiple-use principles. Use of the watershed need not be confined to water production, though that use should be primary.
Miller's crusade to restore the protections of the Trespass Act continued after 1977, and, with the public scrutiny that he inspired, serious degradation of the watershed diminished. His efforts included further litigation and stays to stop what he considered to be dubious timber sales after “blowdowns.”
Images document Joseph L. Miller's crusade to protect the Bull Run Reserve and watershed from logging and recreation damage and to expand public awareness of the threat to its famed pristine water through formation of the Bull Run Interest Group (BRIG) and lawsuits he initiated against the U.S. Forest Service. Bull Run is the main source of water for Portland, Or., and other smaller communities in the area. Photographs showing the impact of logging on the Bull Run Watershed make up the bulk of the collection. Primary formats represented are black-and-white and color photographic prints, ranging from snapshot size to 8x10 (some with negatives), black-and-white and color aerial photographs, and 35 mm color slides. Some prints are attached to two posters, and the collection also includes two color postcards and related papers.
Miller made some of the photographs himself and obtained the remainder from other photographers and sources, including the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers and U.S. Forest Service. Many of the black-and-white and color images were used to illustrate publications produced by BRIG and by Miller personally, and two groups are marked as exhibits in class action lawsuits that Miller and others brought against the U.S. Forest Service.
The photographs are organized into the following series:
Series A: Joseph L. Miller: Background and Portraits, 1990-2004
Series B: Bull Run Interest Group (BRIG) Open Files, 1972-1986
Series C: Lawsuit Exhibits, 1974-1978
Series D: Forest Service Management and Timber Sales, 1927-1991
Subseries 1: Bull Run Watershed, 1927-1981
Subseries 2: Little Sandy River Watershed, 1987-1991
Series E: Images Used in Publications, 1975-1986
Series F: Other Images, ca. 1980-1982; undated
The collection is open to the public.
Joseph L. Miller gave his photographs and papers to the Oregon Historical Society in two parts, 1997 and 1998, with annotations added for clarification shortly before his final donation.
Library accession nos. 23189 and 23563.
Manuscript materials were separated to the Joseph L. Miller Papers, Mss 6022, in the Oregon Historical Society Research Library Manuscripts Collection. Copies of the Bull Run Open Newsletter are available in the Research Library Serials Collection.
Bull Run Interest Group and Miller, Joseph L., comp. Bull Run: A World Treasure: Portland: Bull Run Interest Group, 1998.
Harmon, Rick. "The Bull Run Watershed: Portland's Enduring Jewel." Oregon Historical Quarterly 96 (1995): 242-270.
Miller, Joseph L., Jr. How to Destroy God's Kingdom and Democracy at the Same Time: Case Study, Water Supply of Portland, Oregon. Portland: J.L. Miller, 1989.
Miller, Joseph L. and John Eliot Allen. What Good Is Free Speech in a Closet?: A Story of Cover-up in Planning for Our Grandchildren's Drinking Water. Porland, Or.: DRC Graphics Services, 1985.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Miller, Joseph L., 1910- --Photographs.
Portland (Or.). Water Bureau--Photographs.; United States. Forest Service--Photographs.; United States. Army. Corps of Engineers.; United States. Forest Service.
Bull Run River Watershed (Or.)--Photographs.; Little Sandy River Watershed (Or.)--Photographs.; Mount Hood National Forest (Or.)--Photographs.
Drinking water--Oregon--Portland.; Logging--Oregon--Mount Hood National Forest--Photographs.; Public works--Oregon--Portland--Photographs.; Water supply--Oregon--Portland--Photographs.; Water quality--Oregon--Bull Run River Watershed.; Watershed management--Oregon--Portland--Photographs.
Oregon; Portland; Environmental Conditions; Logging
Aerial photographs.; Film negatives.; Photographic prints.; Slides.
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Joseph L. Miller: Background and Portraits, 1990-2004; Series A; 8 items
  Includes black-and-white and color photographic prints.
  - Background, 2004 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Portraits, ca. 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1/2)
    Black-and-white mages by Jeanne Fromuth and Alberta Gerould
  - At the Stand for Ancient Forests Earth Day event, April 21, 1990 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - At Portland City Council hearings, 1992 or 1993 (Box-folder 1/4)
    35mm slides by Brad Yazzolino. People pictured in addition at Miller are Bob Robinson, Doug Christie, and Alberta [?]
- Bull Run Interest Group (BRIG) Open Files, 1972-1986; Series B; 307 items
  Includes photographic prints, aerial photographs, and slides that are part of Joseph Miller’s version of the BRIG Open File of background materials established at the Multnomah County Library, where they were indexed and are available to the public. Miller’s idea was that the Open File would be “a live, growing source of information on all sides of Bull Run issues. The file is open for anyone to add information or views; for anyone to help seek and index new material; for anyone to study.” The primary version of the file remains available in the Multnomah County Central Library (Portland, Or.) Government Documents Room (2004).
  The series is arranged numerically by the BRIG Open File numbers the photographs are drawn from (see Joseph L. Miller Papers, Mss 6022). It also includes a small poster with prints, showing the card index to the Open File, and some photographic reproductions and photocopies of maps used in various files.
  - BRIG Open File poster, ca. 1975 (Box-folder 1/5)
    Includes two color prints on 8-in. x 8-in. cardboard, advertising availability of the Open File at the Multnomah County Central Library (Portland, Or)
  - No. 61--Helicopter logging in Bull Run Reserve, Aug. 29, 1975 (Box-folder 1/6)
    Color images by Spencer Beebe, printed four to an 8 x 10-in. sheet, with captions. Includes some duplicates.
  - No. 67--Slide show, undated (Box-folder 1/7)
    One slide only, no slide show. Color slide No. 2 shows Bull Run Reserve boundaries. File includes related correspondence and notes. Location of the slide show is unknown. It is not with the BRIG Open File at the Multnomah County Central Library.
  - No. 117--maps reproduced from Bull Run Draft Environmental Impact Statement (U.S. Forest Service), 1976 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - No. 126--images of logging impacts on Bull Run Watershed, 1976 (Box-folder 1/9)
    Color prints and list, including images of Goodfellow Lakes and Little Sandy River Watershed.
  - No. 126--maps reproduced from Bull Run Draft Environmental Impact Statement (U.S. Forest Service), 1976 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - No. 126--aerial photographs of Bull Run Watershed (Oregon State Department of Forestry), June 28, 1972 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - No. 139--color photographic reproductions of hand annotated maps, Bull Run Watershed, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
  - No. 139--Bull Run Reserve black-and-white aerials, 1974 (Box-folder Over A/1)
    Some annotated with boundaries in plastic tape and felt tip marker
  - No. 257d-i--Bull Run Watershed clearcuts, 1978 (Box-folder 1/13)
    Color prints by Douglas Larson. Includes notation that Joseph L. Miller sent copies of the photographs to the mayor of Portland in 1985.
  - No. 275--tour to select sites for proposed Bull Run Monitoring by citizens group--color prints, May 6, 1986 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - No. 275.2--tour to select sites for proposed Bull Run Monitoring by citizens group--color prints, July 14, 1986 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - No. 275-275.2--tour to select sites for proposed Bull Run Monitoring by citizens group--35 mm color slides, May-July 1986 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - No. 277--color prints used in Free Speech Out of the Closet, Aug. 7, 1986 (Box-folder 1/17)
    Nanny Creek Blowdown timber sale.
  - No. 307e--color image on information sheet, Little Sandy River Drainage, 1987 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - BRIG Open Files--maps of roadless areas, Bull Run Watershed, undated (Box-folder 1/19)
    Color photographic reproductions of hand annotated maps.
  - BRIG Open Files--maps collected for use, Bull Run Watershed, undated (Box-folder 1/120)
    Photographic reproductions and photocopies.
  - BRIG Open Files--maps--notes and orders, 1974-1984 (Box-folder 1/21)
- Photographic Exhibits for Lawsuits, 1974-1978; Series C; 103 items
  Includes color and black-and-white photographic prints marked as exhibits for two class action lawsuits that Joseph L. Miller and others initiated against U.S. Forest Service management practices on the Mount Hood National Forest. This included Miller vs. Mallory, charging the U.S. Forest Service was in violation of the Trespass Act, and Miller vs. Robertson, asking a U.S. District Court Judge to halt several "blowdown" timber sales offered by the Forest Service. Dates listed for folders are dates the photographs were made, if known, or dates they were entered as exhibits.
  - Miller vs. Mallory, Aug. 29, 1974 (Box-folder 1/22)
    Color prints of helicopter logging in Bull Run Watershed, made by Spencer Beebe (see also folder 1/6 in this collection). Includes photocopy of Beebe's brief diary of the trip and list of images he made.
  - Miller vs. Mallory, February 1974 (Box-folder 1/23)
    Color prints showing logging impacts on the Bull Run Watershed.
  - Miller vs. Robertson--photographic prints from U.S. Forest Service brief, 1978 (Box-folder 1/24)
    Includes color prints (some assembled as glued-up composites to form panoramas) and black-and-white photographic prints. Removed from Miller Papers, Mss 6022, 31/6.
- Forest Service Management and Timber Sales, 1927-1991; 1973-1987; Series D; 132 items
  Consists primarily of color prints and slides illustrating the impacts of logging on the Bull Run and Little Sandy River watersheds. One 1927 black-and-white image shows the site of a dam built on the Bull Run River to create the reservoir from which Portland draws its water supply.
  - Bull Run Watershed, 1927-ca. 1981; 1973-1977; Subseries 1; 115 items
    - Bull Run dam site, 1927 (Box-folder 1/25)
      Black-and-white print by David B. Charlton.
    - Forest Service closure notices for Bull Run Watershed, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 1/26)
      Color prints of notice tacked to trees that cites the 1904 Trespass Act.
    - Logging impacts--color prints, January 1974 (Box-folder 1/27)
      Notation indicates copies of these were sent to "Charley" [Charles Merten, attorney in class action lawsuits].
    - Logging impacts--color prints, February 1974 (Box-folder 1/28)
    - Logging impacts--color prints, 1974 (Box-folder 1/29)
    - "Petition to Protect Our Bull Run Water from Commercial Logging and Public Recreation"--poster with neck cord, ca. 1974 (Box-folder Over B-1/1)
      Includes copies of two color prints by Spencer Beebe, Aug. 29, 1974--see 1/6 for originals.
    - Infrared views of Bull Run Watershed from U-2 plane at 65,000 feet--35mm color slides, 1974 (Box-folder 1/30)
      By U.S. Army Corps of Engineers
    - Logging on Barium and Uranium timber sales (U.S. Forest Service)--color prints, 1977 (Box-folder 1/31)
    - Logging on Swampy timber sale (U.S. Forest Service)--color prints, 1977 (Box-folder 1/32)
    - Blowdown sale areas areas planned by U.S. Forest Service--35 mm color slides, ca. 1977 (Box-folder 1/33)
    - Blowdown--color print, undated (Box-folder 1/34)
  - Little Sandy River Watershed, 1987-1991; Subseries 2; 17 items
    - Views--color prints, Sept. 30, 1987 (Box-folder 1/35)
    - Views--black-and-white prints, Oct. 30, 1987 (Box-folder 1/36)
    - Proposed logging areas--Cowboy, Olive and Quiver timber sales, 1987 (Box-folder 1/37)
      Two color prints on two-sided bulletin paste-up used for photocopying.
    - Circle and Pica timber sales, Zigzag Ranger District, April 1988 (Box-folder 1/38)
      Two black-and-white prints on two-sided paste-up used for photocopying Free Speech Out of the Closet, No. 67, April 21, 1988.
    - Olive Planning Unit, U.S. Forest Service--color photo sheet with captions, May 1990 (Box-folder Over A/2)
    - Olive Planning Unit, U.S. Forest Service--color prints, October-November 1991 (Box-folder 1/39)
- Images Used in Publications, 1975-1986; Series E; 14 items
  - Bull Run Open Newsletter, Oct. 1, 1975 (Box-folder 1/40)
    Four color prints on paste-up used for photocopying.
  - Free Speech Out of the Closet color print, July 14, 1986 (Box-folder 1/41)
  - Free Speech Out of the Closet--color prints, Aug. 7, 1986 (Box-folder 1/42)
    See Joseph L. Miller Papers, Mss 6022, 50/6 and 7.
- Other Images, ca. 1980; 1982; undated; Series F; 4 items
  - Breitenbush River Drainage (Or.), Devil's Ridge section--color aerial photograph, 1982 (Box-folder 1/43)
  - Other images, ca. 1980; undated
    - Publick Occurrences (first newspaper in America)--color print of exhibit panel, ca. 1980 (Box-folder 1/44)
    - Douglas fir display, Robert B. Pamplin Forest Research Center (Mosby Creek, Or.)--color postcard [2 copies], undated (Box-folder 1/44)